<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The povver of love.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W690A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1206_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867705</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867705</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169467</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97103)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169467)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 168:E1206[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The povver of love.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.C. for John Sweeting, at the signe of the Angell in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By William Walwyn.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169467:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POWER OF LOVE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. C.</hi> for <hi>John Sweeting,</hi> at the ſigne of the Angell in Popes-head Alley.</p>
            <p>1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169467:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169467:2"/>
            <head>To every Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or there is no reſpect of perſons with God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and whoſoever is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with love, judgeth no longer as a man, but god-like, as a true Chriſtian. What's here towards? (ſayes one) ſure one of the Family of love: very well! pray ſtand ſtill and conſider: what family are you of I pray? are you of Gods family? no doubt you are: why, God is love, and if you bee one of Gods children be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of your Father, nor his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and bee aſſured that in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,
<pb facs="tcp:169467:3"/> he regards neither fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> clothes, nor gold rings, nor ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſes, nor abundance of wealth nor dignities, and titles of honour, nor any mans birth or calling, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he regards nothing among his children but love. Conſider our Saviour ſaith, He that hath this worlds goods, and ſeeth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lack, how dwelleth the love of God in him? Judge then by this rule who are of Gods family; looke about and you will finde in theſe woefull dayes thouſands of miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, diſtreſſed, ſtarved, impriſoned Chriſtians: ſee how pale and wan they looke: how coldly, raggedly, &amp; unwholſomely they are cloathed? live one weeke with them in their poore houſes, lodge as they lodge,
<pb facs="tcp:169467:3"/> eate as they eate, and no oftner, and bee at the ſame paſſe to get that wretched food for a ſickly wife, and hunger-ſtarved chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; (if you dare doe this for feare of death or diſeaſes) then walke abroad, and obſerve the generall plenty of all neceſſaries, obſerve the gallant bravery of multitudes of men and women a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in all things that can be imagined: obſerve likewiſe the innumerable numbers of thoſe that have more then ſufficeth. Neither will I limit you to obſerve the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate people of the world, but the whole body of religious people themſelves, and in the very Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and upon ſolemne dayes: view them well, and ſee whether they
<pb facs="tcp:169467:4"/> have not this worlds goods; their ſilkes, their beavers, their rings, and other diviſes will teſtifie they have; I, and the wants and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes of the poore will teſtifie that the love of God they have not. What is here aimed at? (ſayes another) would you have all things common? for love ſeeketh not her owne good, but the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. You ſay very true, it is the Apoſtles doctrine: and you may remember the multitude of beleevers had all things common: that was another of their opinions, which many good people are afraid of. But (ſayes another) what would you have? would you have no diſtinct on of men, nor no government? feare it not: nor
<pb facs="tcp:169467:4"/> flye the truth becauſe it ſuites not with your corrupt opinions or cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; on Gods name diſtinguiſh of men and women too, as you ſee the love of God abound in them towards their brethren, but no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; And for that great mountaine (in your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) government, 'tis but a mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill if you would handle it fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly, and bee bold with it: It is common agreement to bee ſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned: and by common agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment men chuſe for governours, ſuch as their vertue and wiſedome make ſit to governe: what a huge thing this matter of truſt is made of? and what cauſe is there that men that are choſen ſhould keepe at ſuch diſtance, or thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:169467:5"/> have choſen them bee ſo ſheepiſh in their preſence? Come, you are mightily afraid of opinions, is there no other that you feare? not the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Browniſts,</hi> or <hi>Antinomians?</hi> Why doe you ſtart man? have a little patience, would you truly underſtand what kinde of people theſe are, and what opinions they hold? If you would; bee adviſed by ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, and with him conſult what hath learnedly beene written of the moſt weake and and vitious amongſt any of them that could bee found, and make your conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (according to cuſtome) that they are all ſuch: but if you would free your ſelves from common mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes concerning thoſe your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="tcp:169467:5"/> then acquaint your ſelves with them, obſerve their wayes, and enquire into their doctrines your ſelfe, and ſo make your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, or judge not of them; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit them, heare them out, ſtand cleare from all prejudging: and then ſee what dangerous people they are that are generally ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: particulars being abſurd rules of judging; for ſo the <hi>Turke</hi> is miſled in his judgment of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: and no marvaile ſince hee judgeth thereof by the doctrine and life of the moſt ſuperſtitious, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous, and vitious amongſt them. Well, what next are you afraid of? for ſome men take delight to be under the ſpirit of bondage, and doe not think themſelves in good
<pb facs="tcp:169467:6"/> eſtate except they be in feare: but come, feare nothing, you are advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Apoſtle to try all things, and to hold faſt that which is good: to prove the Spirits whether they bee of God or not: 'tis your ſelfe muſt doe it, you are not to truſt to the authority of any man, or to any mans relation: you will finde upon tryall that ſcarcely any opinion hath beene reported truly to you: and though in every one of them you may finde ſome things that you cannot agree unto, you will yet be a gainer, by diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring many excellent things that you as yet may be unſatisfied in, and by due conſideration of them all perfect your owne judgement. Reade the enſuing diſcourſe impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, and you will finde the minde
<pb facs="tcp:169467:6"/> of him that hateth no man for his opinion; nor would have any man troubled for any opinion, except ſuch, as make the bloud of Chriſt ineffectuall, or ſuch as would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all that will not ſubmit to their opinions; hee ſeemes to bee of the Apoſtles minde, that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered all other things in love: (and that in matters of moment too, even where ſome obſerved a day unto the Lord, &amp; others not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) He bids you walke in love, as Chriſt hath loved you, and gave himſelfe for you, an offering and a Sacrifice; you that love your brother ſo poorely, as that you cannot allow him the peaceable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of his mind and judgment would hardly lay downe your life for him; let brotherly love conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,
<pb facs="tcp:169467:7"/> and let every one freely ſpeake his minde without moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and ſo there may be hope that truth may come to light, that otherwiſe may be obſcured for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ends: plaine truth will prove all, ſufficient for vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the moſt artificiall, ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call errour that ever was in the world; give her but due and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent audience, and her perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ten thouſand times more powerfull to worke upon the moſt dull refractory minde, then all the adulterate allurements and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings of art. What is here pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht is out of fervent love to the Communion of Chriſtians: that they might taſt and ſee how good the Lord is, In whoſe preſence
<pb facs="tcp:169467:7"/> there is fulneſſe of joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for evermore: Wherefore rejoyce in the Lord alwayes, and againe I ſay rejoyce: and let your ſong bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, Glory be to God on high, in earth peace, good will towards men. Let truth have her free and perfect working, and the iſſue will bee increaſe of beleevers: let faith have her perfect working, and the iſſue will bee increaſe of love: and let love have her perfect working, and the whole world will be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, that God will be all in all; for hee that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in God, in whom, ever fare you well, and bee cheerefull.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169467:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169467:8"/>
            <head>THE POVVER OF LOVE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Tit. 2. 11, 12.</bibl>
               <q>The grace (or love) of God that bringeth ſalvation unto all men hath appeared, teaching us to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, &amp; godly in this preſent world.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is evident (though it be little regarded or conſidered, the more is the pity) that in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall things all things whatſoever
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169467:9"/> that are neceſſary for the uſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, the uſe of them is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood eaſily with out ſtudy or difficulty: every Capacity is capable thereof; and not only ſo, but they are all likewiſe ready at hand, or eaſily to be had: a bleſſing that God hath afforded to every man, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that there is no part of the habitable world, but yeeldes ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of uſefull things for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and pleaſant ſuſtentation of the inhabitants; as experience teſtifieth in all places; and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed that God left himſelfe not without witneſſe, in that he did good, gave them raine from heaven, and fruitfull ſeaſons, feeding their hearts with foode and gladneſſe: by all which it plainely appeares; that God ever intendeth unto man a pleaſant and comfortable life: you know it is ſaid, that God made man righteous, but he ſought out many
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169467:9"/> inventions: that is, he made him naturally a rationall creature, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly of all things, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring only what was neceſſary, and ſo being exempt from all labour, and care of obtaining things ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, he paſſed his dayes with aboundance of delight and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: until he ſought out unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe many inventions: inventions of ſuperfiuous ſubtilities and artificiall things, which have beene multiplied with the ages of the world, every age ſtill producing new: ſo now in theſe latter times we ſee nothing but mens inventions in eſteeme, and the newer the more precious; if I ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in particulars, I ſhould or might be endleſſe, as in diet, your ſelves know to your coſts, (for it coſts you not only your monyes, but your healths, and length of dayes) that this fruitfull nation ſufficeth not to furniſh ſcarce the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169467:10"/> meaneſt meale you make, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be had to pleaſe the luxurious palate from forraine and farre countryes: and ever the farther the better, and the dearer the more acceptable; you know likewiſe the exceſſive proviſion that is made for entertainments and ſet meetings, where all groſſe meates (you know my meaning) muſt be baniſhed, and nothing admitted but what is rare and fine, and full of invention, in the dreſſes, ſauces, and manner of ſervice: where all the ſenſes muſt be pleaſed to the heighth of all poſſible conceipt. If I ſhould reckon up your new inventions for buildings, and furniture for your houſes, and the common coſtlineſſe of your apparell, and ſhould ſet before you the manifold vexations, perplexities, diſtractions, cares, and inconveniences that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew unto you by theſe your vaine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169467:10"/> and ridiculous follies, I might be endleſſe therein alſo, and loſe my labour; for there is no hope that I ſhould prevaile for a reformation of theſe things, when your daily experience ſcourges you continually therunto, in one kind or other, and all in vaine; yet I ſhall take leave to tell you that in theſe things, you walke not as becommeth the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but are carnall and walke as men, as vaine, fantaſticall, inconſiderate men; ſuch as very heathen and meere naturall men would be a ſhamed of: their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience (that a life according to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to be content with little, with what was ever ready, and eaſy to be had, was the moſt pleaſant life and exempt from all vexations) was inſtruction ſufficient unto many of them, to frame themſelves thereunto, and to abandon all kindes of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities, without retaining the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169467:11"/> leaſt; &amp; thereby obtained a freedome to apply themſelves to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and practiſe of wiſedome and vertue.</p>
            <p>It is a wonderfull thing to my underſtanding, that men ſhould call themſelves Chriſtians, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to be religious, and to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent readers of Scripture, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Sermons, and yet content themſelves to bee indeed in many things carnall, and to walke as did the moſt indiſcreete and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Gentiles. Doth the Scripture teach no more then nature teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? though it doe infinitely, yet your practiſe compared with wiſe conſiderate naturall men declares it doth not; how extreamely then (thinke you) doe you cauſe the name of God to be blaſphemed? Doe you thinke it is ſufficient that you are not drunkards, nor adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, nor uſurers, nor contentious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169467:11"/> perſons, nor covetous? beloved, if you will truely deſerve the name of Chriſtians, it is not ſufficient: but you are to abandon all ſuperfluities, all poring after vaine ſuperfluous things, and thereby to exempt your ſelves from all unneceſſary cares that choake the Word, and bee at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to conſider, and to apply your ſelves freely to the continuall contemplation of the infinite love of God, evidently and plainely ſet forth unto you in his bleſſed word: as in the words that I have read un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>you: for as it is in naturall things, ſo holds it in ſpirituall: God hath dealt abundantly well with us; there being nothing that is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry either for the enlightning of our underſtandings, or the peace of our mindes, but what hee hath plainely declared and manifeſtly ſet forth in his Word: ſo plainely, that the meaneſt capacity is fully capable of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169467:12"/> a right underſtanding thereof, and need not to doubt but that he is ſo. I will not ſay that God is not more good unto us, then we are hurtfull to our ſelves, (for his goodneſſe is more availeable to our welfare, then our evill can be to our miſery) but wee are as evill to our ſelves in all things as we can be poſſible: and that not onely in naturall things, but likewiſe in ſpirituall and divine things too, for therein alſo we have our inventions; the plaine and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident places of Scripture manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declaring our peace and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God, is become nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous to us: they make ſalvation too eaſie to be underſtood, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it upon too eaſie tearmes, and too generall: this <hi>Manna</hi> that comes to us without our labour, induſtry, ſtudy, and watching, is two fulſome, ſomething that hath bones in it muſt bee found out, and will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169467:12"/> more acceptable: every child or babe in Chriſts Schoole can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe: We are full growne men in Chriſt, wee have ſpent our time in long and painefull ſtudies, and have full knowledge in all Arts and ſciences: there is no place of Scripture too hard for us: ſhew us the myſteries we cannot reveale: the Parables that wee cannot clearely open: the Propheſies that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not interpret: a word or Syllable that wee cannot fitly apply, or the moſt palpable ſeeming contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that we cannot reconcile; nay it is to be doubted (wee have ſeene the vaine humour of man puft ſo high, and the world ſo fill'd and peſtered with works and labours of this vaine nature) leſt there are ſome ſuch daring undertakers, that like as <hi>Alexander</hi> the great is ſaid to have wept that there were no more worlds to conquer, ſo theſe Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169467:13"/> are grieved that there are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> harder places for their braines to worke upon: or (which is more to bee lamented) one would fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they are much troubled that the moſt neceſſary truths are ſo eaſie to be underſtood: for that when they treate upon ſome very plaine place of Scripture, even ſo plaine as thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which I have read unto you, yet in handling thereof they make it diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, and darken the cleare meaning thereof with their forced and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall gloſſes: but as I wiſh there were no ſuch dealers in divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things, ſo have I in my ſelfe reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to avoid theſe extreame evills: for as in naturall things I am fully aſſured there is nothing of neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſe but what is eaſily underſtood and even ready at hand, ſo alſo doth my experience tell me, that we have no bettering of our underſtandings, or quieting of our mindes (the end
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169467:13"/> for which God hath vouchſafed his word) from any places of Scripture that hath any obſcurity in them, but from ſuch as are clearely exempt from all difficulty. You know God frequently complaines by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſaying, My people will not conſider, they will not underſtand: and when I conſider that your owne experience ſchooles you not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently againſt your dotage upon the vaine ſuperfluities of this world, wherein you know your ſelves to be carnall, and to walke as men, heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto your ſelves vexation upon vexation; I doe wonder that it doth not ſtagger the Miniſters of God in their publiſhing of things divine to a people ſo qualified, ſo extreamely inconſiderate: indeed it would make one to ſuſpect the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that you continually heare, that it were not powerfull nor from heaven, but weake and fitted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169467:14"/> to your corrupt humours, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, ſince after ſo long time, it hath not ſubdued your worldly mindedneſſe. Sure I am, and I muſt have leave to tell you, that there is utterly a fault amongſt you, nay thoſe expreſſions are too ſoft, you have almoſt nothing but faults a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, and you will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, which you muſt doe, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly too, or you will never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce your ſelves into ſuch a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as will be really ſutable to the bleſſed name of Chriſtians. Beloved I have ſeriouſly conſidered it, and it is not your caſe alone, but it is the univerſall diſeaſe. I know not any that is not infected therewith, nor to whom it may not be ſaid, Phyſitian heale thy ſelfe; the milke we have ſuckt, and the common ayre hath beene totally corrupted: our firſt inſtructions, and all after diſcourſes have beene indulgent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169467:14"/> flatterers to our darling ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and therefore he that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the cure, muſt bee ſure to bee provided of a fit and powerfull me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, and to be diligent and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in his undertaking; it is a taske that I have propoſed unto my ſelfe, and though I ſhould meete with the greateſt diſcouragements, (as, the world is like enough to furniſh his utmoſt forces to preſerve his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) yet conſidering whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I have undertaken, and whoſe works it is, I ſhall not deſpaire of ſucceſſe. I am not ignorant that this worke hath often-times beene at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, and perſiſted in: but with little fruit; through the univerſall miſtake, that men are ſooner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded from their vanities, through preſſures of the law, and affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing terrors of wrath and hell, then by the cordes of love: which yet I abundantly preferre, as you may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169467:15"/> perceive by this text which I have choſen: for when all is done, It is the love of God bringing ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that teacheth us to deny all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world. I muſt entreate your moſt carneſt attention, as being full of hope that I ſhall doe you much more good then you conceive: for I muſt tell you, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not cure you of your earthly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedneſſe, of your dotage upon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities, till I have firſt ſhowne you your peace and reconciliation with God, and have wrought in you (through the power of Gods word) peace of conſcience and joy in the holy Ghoſt. You are then ſeriouſly to conſider what is ſaid, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding will ſucceed. The love of God I know is often ſpoken of: a theame that hath begotten abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of bookes and diſcourſes: yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169467:15"/> none in no compariſon like the Scriptures: moſt (if not all) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, that ever I have read or heard, doe in ſome ſenſe or other, or in in ſome meaſure injure and wrong thoſe bleſſed diſcourſes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>The love and favour of God (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) is better then life it ſelfe; What man in the whole world doth not gladly heare the joyfull tydings of the love of God? But it is good that every man right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand, and miſtake not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this ſo bleſſed and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subject. I ſhall lay downe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome infallible principles which concerne the ſame. And I ſhall tell you nothing but what your ſelves know: and that is, that God doth moſt vehemently hate all manner of ſinnes, and that it is impoſſible for him to doe otherwiſe, as being directly oppoſite to his moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169467:16"/> nature: and to that righteous nature wherein at firſt man was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, for in the likeneſſe of God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated he him: and whilſt you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this, I ſhall adviſe you not to flatter your ſelves as the Phariſee did, ſaying, Lord I thanke thee I am not as other men, extortioners, unjuſt, adulterers, drunkards, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, proude, or licentious; can you ſay you have noe ſinne? if you ſhould, the word of God would contradict you, which teſtifieth that he that ſaith he hath no ſinne is a liar, and the truth is not in him; and if ſinne be in every one, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily it followes where ſinne is, there is Gods hatred; nor doeth it any whit excuſe or exempt thoſe from the hatred of God, that can ſay their ſinnes are fewe in number, and of very meane condition com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to others: whoſoever you are that are thus indulgent to your
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169467:16"/> ſelves, you doe but deceive your ſelves, for Gods hatred, his wrath and anger, is ſo exact againſt all and every ſinne, and ſo odious it is in his ſight, than he denounceth, ſaying, Curſed is every one that continueth not to doe all that is written in the booke of the law: So as every mouth muſt be ſtopped, and all the world ſtand guilty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; and though the ſenſe and deepe apprehenſion of this woefull condition, doe worke in you the deepeſt of ſorrow, though you ſhould ſpend your dayes in weeping, and your nights in woefull lamentation, though you ſhould repent your ſelves in duſt and aſhes, and cover your ſelves with ſackcloathes: though you ſhould faſt yourſelves into paleneſſe, and hang downe your heads al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes: though you ſhould give all your goods to the poore; nay,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169467:17"/> though you ſhould offer up the fruit of your bodies, for the ſinne of your ſoules; all this and more could be no ſatisfaction for the leaſt ſinne, nor bring any peace to your mindes: but you muſt of force cry out at laſt, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, (ſtating this ſad condition of all mankind under the law) <hi>Ob wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from this body of death!</hi> Juſtly is it called a body of death; for man is of a fraile and weake condition at the beſt: a conſiderate man hath death alwayes before him: What joy or comfort then can hee take all his life long; being in the hatred of God, a veſſell of wrath, and liable to eternall death in hell fire for ever? What can he looke upon that can give him content? Preſent a man that walkes in the ſenſe of his ſinfull condition, with all the pleaſures the world afford,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169467:17"/> and his ſad heart turnes all into death; his conſcience continually afflicts him; terrours, and feares, and eternall torments are ever in his thoughts: and ſuch a wounded Spirit, who can beare? My beloved, I would not be miſtaken in what I have ſaid of this woefull condition, as though I preſented it to your thoughts, as a meanes to terrifie you from any your ſinfull courſes: I know full well it is not the way, it is not Gods way: nor doe I wiſh this ſad condition to be any of yours: though happily it may be thus with many of you: many of you may through ſenſe of ſinne, and of wrath due for ſinne, walke in a very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate condition: feares and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours may abound in you: to whom (I doubt not) though great heavineſſe may indure for a night, yet greater joy ſhall come in the morning: which as much as in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169467:18"/> mee lyes, I ſhall indeavour to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in every one of you.</p>
            <p>I have preſented this woefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all mankind under the law, thus ſadly and truly, becauſe I finde generally men doe not ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider the bottomleſſe depth of the miſery from the which they are redeemed: I am not a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the law, but of the goſpell; nor are you under the law, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace: the law was given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe miniſter I am not: but grace and truth came by Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe miniſter I am: whoſe exceeding love, hath appeared: and becauſe I would have you fully to ſee and conſider his love, therefore did I ſhew the woefull condition, from which only by his love you are delivered.</p>
            <p>Another principle I ſhall pray you to conſider, is that God loves nothing but what is pure and holy,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169467:18"/> without ſpot or blemiſh: ſo as it is a vaine and deluſive doctrin, to ſay that God paſſes by our daily infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, accepting our wills for our performances: our deſire to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to his Commandements, for obedience: for where there is the leaſt defect, God hates for that very defect, and loves not but where there is perfect holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: which makes this truth appeare, that by the deeds of the law ſhall no fleſh be iuſtified in his ſight: for by the law is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne. It is a ſad favour that the law ever did unto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, to make his ſinne appeare out of meaſure ſinfull, ſtopping every mans mouth, admitting no plea or excuſe on mans behalfe; And yet it is ſo naturall to thinke that he is ſtill bound to doe ſomething for obtaining the love and favour of God, that you will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169467:19"/> finde it is the hardeſt thing in the world to free your ſelves from it, though it be the groſſeſt Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian errour that ever was; for if righteouſneſſe come by the law, then Chriſt died in vaine; It it ſuch an errour that untill it be removed out of your mindes, it will be but labour loſt to endeavour to worke any truth upon your mindes; and I have much cauſe, to feare your mindes are tainted therewith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our publicke catechiſmes, bookes, and Sermons are for the moſt part corrupted therewith, ſo as we ſucke this errour in even with our very milke, and it becomes one ſubſtance with many of us even to our old age; It was ſo in the Apoſtles times, as may be ſeene in <hi>Acts</hi> the 15, from the 5. verſe to the end of the chapter, where you ſhall find that ſome that beleeved affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that it was neceſſary to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169467:19"/> and to keepe the law: but you will finde by the ſtory it was their errour; Alſo in the ſecond to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the third to the end, where you ſhall find the law ſtiled the miniſtration of death, written in tables of ſtone (which was the 10 Commandements) and verſe the 11. to be done away, and a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious miniſtration to take place and remaine: and yet the breeding of the <hi>Iewes</hi> being under the law, (though they did beleeve the comming of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) yet ſtill (even to that day the Apoſtle wrote) their minds were blinded, and the vaile remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the reading of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which vayle is done away in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Theſe things (beloved) you are to conſider ſeriouſly, for that untill you doe undoubtedly ſee your ſelves not to be under the law, no not in the leaſt reſpect, you cannot ſee your ſelves to be under
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169467:20"/> grace: that is, in the favour and love of God, untill when you cannot with ſound judgment affirme, that which my text affirmeth, that is, that the love of God hath appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for he that in any meaſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth himſelfe to be under the law, doth not clearely diſcerne the love of god: for that vayle is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes; you all give credit to the word of God: let S. <hi>Paul</hi> then be your guide to leade you out of this ſad Aegyptian bondage who knew all things that concerned the law, yet cryes out, I account all things as loſſe and dung, that I may be found in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not having my owne (or mans) righteouſneſſe, which is of the law, but the righteouſneſſe which is of God in him: make it your own caſes by ſound conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for yee are all juſtified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> your feares,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169467:20"/> nor ſinnes, nor doubtings, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alter that condition which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath purchaſed for you, for though the ſting of death be ſinne, &amp; the ſtrength of ſin be the law, yet thankes be unto God, for he hath given us the victory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: ſo as you may all boldly ſay, Oh death where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory? And that none of you may doubt of his exceeding love, and your perfect reconciliation with God, I wil reade unto you certaine paſſages (in the 5 chapter, to the <hi>Romans,</hi>) which if well weighed, will leave you without all ſcruple, (verſe,6) When we were yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtrength in due time Chriſt died for the ungodly: you ſee there that ungodlineſſe did not hinder, but that Chriſt died for thee that art ungodly: doſt thou ſtand amazed, and canſt not throwly beleeve? the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169467:21"/> Apoſtle grants that to mans judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is incredible; for amongſt men, ſcarcely for a righteous man will one dye, yet peradventure for a good man one would even dare to dye: but to confirme thy timerous heart (verſe 8.) God commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his love towards us, in that whilſt we were yet ſinners Chriſt died for us, (<hi>v.</hi> 9.) much more being then juſtified by his bloud we ſhall be ſaved from wrath through him, (<hi>v.</hi> 10.) for if when we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, we were reconciled by the death of his Sonne, much more being reconciled, we ſhall be ſaved by his life: ſo as now thou haſt cauſe to joy in God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom thou haſt received the atonement: and to take from thee all ſtaggering (in the 18. <hi>v.</hi>) he confirmes thee, ſaying, As by the offence of one, judgement came upon all men to condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169467:21"/> even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, the free gift came upon all men to juſtification of life: and (in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he 20. <hi>verſ.</hi>) becauſe he knew thy proneneſſe to make queſtions ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Law, he tels thee the Law entred that ſinne might abound, but withall aſſures thee, that where ſinne abounded, grace (or love) did much more abound: that as ſinne had reigned unto death, even ſo grace (or love) might reign through righteouſneſſe unto eternall life through Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>(Beloved) God by the power of his Word hath begotten ſo ful aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of theſe things in me, as that thereby he hath made me an able Miniſter of the New Teſtament: not of the Letter, (or the Law) but of the Spirit: for the Letter killeth, but the Spirit (that is the Goſpel) giveth life. Nor doe I ſee any cauſe why any of you here preſent ſhould
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169467:22"/> ſo much as doubt your ſalvation; I am a Miniſter of reconciliation, and am thereby bound to tell you (for woe is unto me if I preach not the Goſpel, as in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19.) that God was in Chriſt reconciling the world unto himſelfe, not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their treſpaſſes unto them: and hath committed unto us the Word of reconcilation; Now then we are Ambaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray you to be reconciled unto God; for he hath made him to be ſinne for us, that knew no ſinne, that we might be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God in him; ſo as (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we may vainely conceive to our owne prejudice) God conſiders us not as we ſee our ſelves full of ſinne, full of iniquity, but as we ſhould conſider our ſelves, agreeable to all theſe paſſages of his bleſſed Word, fully and perfectly waſhed from all
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169467:22"/> our ſinnes by the bloud of his Son (which every one of us doe beleeve, though we doe not conſider) and then with unſpeakable joy we ſhall ſee that we are reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne: that we are juſtified freely by his grace: that for our loſt righteouſneſſe of the Law, we are made the righteouſneſſe of God In him: having peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and joy in the holy Ghoſt, by whoſe word theſe bleſſed truths are declared unto us. Are theſe things ſo indeed, doth God accept me a poore miſerable ſinner, as righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in his ſight, and freed from ſinne, from all ſinne? Heare ſtill the Word of God, he hath borne our ſinnes in his body on the tree, and it is the bloud of Chriſt that clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee from all ſinne: he by his one oblation once offered, hath made a full, perfect, and ſufficient ſatisfaction, and ſacrifice for the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169467:23"/> ſinnes of the whole world; and if we ſinne, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: and he is the propitiation for our ſinnes; and not for ours onely, but for the ſinnes of the whole world. This worke of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and reconciliation with God was perfected when Chriſt died: and nothing ſhall be able to ſeparate you from his love then purchaſed: neither infidelity, nor impenitencie, nor unthankfulneſſe, nor ſinne, nor any thing whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can make void his purchaſe: no, though with the Jewes you ſhould deny the Lord that bought you: ſo powerful was his bloud-ſhed ding, and of ſo full value for diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of all our debts, paſt, preſent, and to come; ſo infinite is his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo free is his love, and ſo abundantly happy is our condition, though many of us have beene too
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169467:23"/> too ignorant thereof: and for want of this knowledge many of us have walked very uncomfortably, ſpending our time in faſting, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and mourning; in praying, reading, and hearing, and in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of other duties, as you call them, and all to get Chriſt: our feare diſtracts our judgements, that wee conſider not what the Scripture ſets forth unto us: if we did, wee ſhould ſee aparently that it ſets forth ſalvation wrought and perfected for ever: to whom doth it manifeſt the ſame? to ſinners, to the ungodly, to all the world: a worke perfected, depending on no condition, no performance at all; What would people have to give peace to their mindes? you doe wrong your ſelves through nice diſtinctions: the word of God is given to declare theſe truths, and that he is our peace: the word of God you doe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169467:24"/> beleeve, and ſo cannot but be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, the onely end for which it is preſerved unto you: that you might reade, and know, and underſtand your bleſſed condition: for faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God: and you are to looke for no other teſtimony: nor are you to doubt your ſelves: for though your preſent comfort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon your beleeving this word, yet the worke of Chriſt depends not on your beleeving: and though you ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, yet hee is faithfull and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny himſelfe to be your redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, your peace-maker, your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. Men are not pleaſed except ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation be proved to be very difficult to bee obtained, it muſt ſtill depend either on our beleeving, or doing, or repenting, or ſelfe-deniall, or Sabbath-keeping, or ſomething or other, or elſe man is not pleaſed:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169467:24"/> too eaſie? good God! that free love ſhould be ſuſpected: that becauſe it is eaſie to be had, we ſhould put it farre from us; why, God knew full well thou wert dead, he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that thou wert but duſt; ſuppoſe he had required any thing of thee, without which thou ſhouldſt have no part in Chriſt, what a ſad caſe hadſt thou beene in? goe thy wayes, and with cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe poſſeſſe his infinite love, and declare unto thy brethren what the Lord hath done for al our ſouls; tel them that the love of God bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſalvation hath appeared, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to deny all ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world. And I ſhall deſire to know of all that heare me this day, whereof ſome may happily be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the corruptions of this world: for our times though we call
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169467:25"/> them times of light, yet do abound with gluttony, drunkenneſſe, and whoredome, uſury, pride, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and all kinde of wickedneſſe, ſuch as is not to be named amongſt Chriſtians, (what ſhall I ſay to theſe things? it will be in vaine for me to reprove you for them: for men never reforme their vices, till firſt their judgements be well informed, and then they kindly reforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) I ſhall onely demand whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the love of God doth more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare unto you now, then it hath done formerly? ſurely it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but you muſt be ſenſible of his love, it is ſo full and abſolute, ſo free and unexpecting love. How is it poſſible you ſhould heare and not conſider? had it not beene for this unexpreſſible and unexampled love, you had beene eternally wretched and miſerable, companions of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and damned ſpirits in Hell for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169467:25"/> ever, where the Worme never dieth, and the fire never goeth out; me thinkes you ſhould embrace this love with open armes, and meditate thereupon day and night: it deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to be entertained with the greateſt reſpect, and to be eſteemed above ten thouſand lives: for (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) though it comes freely to you, and coſts you nothing, no not ſo much as a ſigh or teare, yet if you read over the ſtory of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours paſſion, and ſufferings, you will finde it was purchaſed at an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive price, exceſſive paines, and exceſſive torments: nay it is even paſt wonder that he that thought it no robbery to be equall to God, ſhould be in the forme of a ſervant, and become obedient to death, even the moſt bitter death of the Croſſe for our ſinnes: that he ſhould be made ſinne for us that knew no ſinne, that we might be made the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169467:26"/> righteouſneſſe of God in him; me thinkes theſe and the like conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſhould be powerfull in your minds, that your ſpirits ſhould even burne within you, untill you found out ſome way to expreſſe your thankfulneſſe for ſo great, ſo infinite love. I cannot ſuſpect the moſt vitious man in the world, but that hearing theſe things his heart will make ſtrict enquiry, what he ſhall render unto the Lord for all his benefits? and his heart once moving in thoughts of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will inſtantly be inflamed with love, which in an inſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines the whole man. God is love, and love makes man God-like; and henceforth let me pray you to marke the workings of love in your owne ſoules, and you ſhall finde that when your long accuſtomed corruptions (by which you have wounded your owne conſciences,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169467:26"/> and brought diſhonour to God, and reproach to the holy name of Chriſtians) doe tempt to the like abominable actions, your love to God that ſo freely hath loved you, will be ſo prevalent with you, that you will reſolve rather to loſe your lives then to ſhow your ſelves ſo baſely ungratefull: the vanities you have delighted in will become odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto you: all your labour will be that your converſation be as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the Goſpel of Chriſt, nay you will ſhunne the very appearance of evill: and if your brother of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you in any kinde whatſoever, you will finde no difficulty to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give; if you doe, doe but thinke of the love wherewith Chriſt hath loved you, and nothing can be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined ſo abominably injurious but you will gladly forgive. And if you have this worlds goods, and that brother lacke, you will rejoyce
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169467:27"/> that you have an occaſion and means to make known unto the world how powerfully the love of God dwelleth in you: you will be able to doe all things through love that ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens you. Love will be as a new light in your underſtandings by which you will judge quite otherwiſe of all things, then formerly you haved on: the vanities and ſuperfluities which in the beginning of my diſcourſe I reckoned up unto you, will ſeeme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious unto you, and you will no longer faſhion your ſelves like unto this world, but will walk as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Goſpel of Chriſt: you will no longer minde high things, but make your ſelves equall to men of low degree: you will no longer value men and women according to their wealth, or outward ſhewes, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their vertue, &amp; as the love of God appeareth in them: nay if you be ſtudious in this worke of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169467:27"/> love, nothing will be more deare unto you then the glory of God (who hath ſo infinitely loved you) ſo as you will be moſt zealouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to whatſoever is oppoſite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, you will ſinde it nothing to hazzard your lives for God, in defence of his truth from errour; in defence of your brother or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour from oppreſſion or tyranny: love makes you no longer your owne but Gods ſervants, and prompts you to doe his will in the puniſhment of all kinde of exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, whether it be breach of oathes, breach of truſt, or any kinde of injuſtice in whomſoever, and to be no reſpecter of perſons; nor will any ones greatneſſe over-ſway or daunt your reſolutions, but you will be bold as Lions, not fearing the faces of men: you will when neede requires, that is, when tyrants and oppreſſors endeavour by might
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169467:28"/> and force to pervert all Lawes, and compacts amongſt men, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the truth of God into a lie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting his ſacred word as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of their unjuſt power, as if any unjuſt power were of God, and were not to be reſiſted: I ſay, ſuch inſolencies as theſe will inflame your zeale, and ſet you all on fire manfully to fight the Lords battell, and to bring into ſubjection thoſe abominable imaginations and ungodly courſes of men: your judgements will be ſo well infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as you will know theſe things are by God referred unto you, and you will not reſigne them up to him, but willingly ſacrifice your lives and fortunes, and all that is neare and deare unto you, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſuffer his name to be ſo blaſphemed, or your innocent bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or your wives and children to become a prey to wicked and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169467:28"/> bloud-thirſty men. The politicians of this world would have religious men to be fooles, not to reſiſt, no by no meanes, leſt you receive dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: urging Gods holy Word, whilſt they proceed in their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable courſes; but (beloved) they will finde that true Chriſtians are of all men the moſt valiant defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the juſt liberties of their Countrey, and the moſt zealous preſervers of true Religion: vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the truths of God with their lives, againſt all ungodlineſſe and unrighteouſneſſe of men: making thereby the whole world to know that true Chriſtianity hates and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres tyranny, oppreſſion, perjury, cruelty, deceipt, and all kinde of filthineſſe; and true Chriſtians to be the moſt impartiall, and moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere puniſhers thereof, and of all kinde of wickedneſſe, of any men whatſoever.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169467:29"/>
            <p>Great is the power of love, for love makes men to bee of one mind: and what can bee too ſtrong for men united in love? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall warne you to marke and conſider thoſe that make divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongſt you. I pray miſtake me not, I doubt you are too apt in this caſe to make a wrong appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: I doe not meane that you ſhould marke thoſe, that are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from you in judgement, with any ridiculous or reproachfull names: but my advice is that you marke thoſe that make diviſions amongſt you, and thoſe are they that have invented a name of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach for every particular diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in judgement: and in their publike Sermons and private diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, endeavour might and maine to keep at the wideſt diſtance, and by odious tales and falſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations make you irreconciliable:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169467:29"/> nay make you even ready to cut one anothers throates; or by this diviſion prepare you for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon adverſaries to cut both yours and theirs too; difference in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there will be, untill love have a more powerfull working in our hearts: wee ſhould therefore like wiſe men at leaſt beare with one anothers infirmities: love will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all that can bee called infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but reſolved malice love it ſelfe will puniſh. Such opinions as are not deſtructive to humane ſociety, nor blaſpheme the worke of our Redemption, may be peaceably endured, and conſidered in love: and in caſe of conſpiracy againſt our common liberty, what a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is it for men to ſtand in ſtrife about petty opinions? for who are all thoſe that are ſo much rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at by our common Preachers?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169467:30"/> who are they ſay they? why, they are the moſt dangerous Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, and Separatiſts: that are enemies to all order and decency, that cry down all learning and all government in the Church, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. (Beloved) to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg theſe things are not true of any of them: it is true, they cannot do al things ſo orderly and decently as they would, becauſe they are hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into corners, and from one cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to another, and are not free to exerciſe their conſciences, as had they liberty they might, and would; And as for learning, as learning goes now adaies, what can any ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious man make of it, but as an Art to deceive and abuſe the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings of men, and to miſlead them to their ruine? if it be not ſo, whence comes it that the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Univerſity men throughout
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169467:30"/> the Kingdome in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are oppoſers of the welfare of the Common-wealth, and are pleaders for abſurdities in government, arguers for ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and corrupt the judgements of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? no man can be ſo ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as to imagine that they conceive it not lawfull, or not uſefull for men to underſtand the Hebrew, Greeke, or Latine: but withall, if they conceive there is no more matter in one language then another, nor no cauſe why men ſhould be ſo proud for underſtanding of languages, as therefore to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to themſelves the ſole dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in all ſpirituall matters; who (I ſay) can blame them for this judgement? they deſire that a mans ability of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169467:31"/> ſhould be proved by the cleare expreſſion of neceſſary truths, rather then by learning: and ſince the Scriptures are now in Engliſh, which at firſt were in Hebrew, Greeke, or Syriack, or what other language; why may not one that underſtands Engliſh onely, both underſtand and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the true meaning of them as well as an Engliſh Hebrician, or Grecian, or Roman whatſoever? I, but ſaies ſome politick lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, a man that doth not underſtand the Originall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, cannot ſo perfectly give the ſenſe of the Scripture, as he that doth: or as one that makes it his ſtudy for ten or twenty yeares together, and hath no other employment: every man being beſt skilled in his owne profeſſion wherein he hath been
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169467:31"/> bred and accuſtomed. I did well to ſay ſome politicke lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man might thus object: for indeed what is here but po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie? for if it be as ſuch men would imply, I pray what are you the better for having the Scripture in your owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: when it was lock'd up in the Latine tongue by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie of <hi>Rome,</hi> you might have had a learned Fryar for your money at any time to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted the ſame: and though now you have it in your owne language, you are taught not to truſt your owne underſtanding, (have a care of your purſes) you muſt have an Univerſity man to interpret the Engliſh, or you are in as bad a caſe as before but not in worſe; for, for your money you may have plenty at
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169467:32"/> your ſervice, &amp; to interpret as beſt ſhall pleaſe your fancie. Let me prevaile with you to free your ſelves from this bondage, and to truſt to your own conſiderations in any thing that is uſefull for your underſtandings and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: and judge more charitably of your brethren, &amp; underſtand what learning is, and to marke thoſe that cauſe diviſions among you, and you ſhal finde that they are learned men, &amp; not unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The learned man muſt live upon the unlearned, and therfore when the unlearned ſhal preſume to know as much as the learned, hath not the learned man cauſe to beſtir his wits, and towrangle too when his Copy-hold is in ſuch danger? I pray what was the cauſe that <hi>Demetr.</hi> and the Craftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cried out, great is <hi>Diana</hi> of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169467:32"/> the Epheſians, whom al <hi>Aſia</hi> and the world worſhip? was it the love to the goddeſſe or her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? no, we find it was their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and particular gaine? What is it els to cry out, great is learning, great are the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who ſhall anſwer an adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary? (money anſwereth all things) ambition, covetouſneſſe, diſdaine, pride, and luxury are the things aimed at: and if it be not ſo, by the fruits you ſhall certainely know. As for government, thoſe that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed are not guilty, for they are enemies onely to uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and innovations, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitances in government: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are haters of tyranny, and all arbitrary power, but no other: and therefore thoſe that falſely accuſe them, are
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169467:33"/> they that cauſe and foment di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions amongſt you: therefore marke them, and be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by their diſſembled inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations to hold you in diviſion, whilſt they have oportunity to make a prey of you. You know there are Wolves in Sheepes cloathing: be wiſe as Serpents, able to diſcover them, innocent as Doves, gently bearing with the infirmities of the weake, having nothing in more eſteeme then love: thus you will anſwer love with love: that hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your owne ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s may conſtantly witnes to your ſelves (what this Scripture expreſſeth) <hi>That the love of God bringing ſalvation to all men hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, teaching you to live ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world:</hi> Now unto him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169467:33"/> that hath loved us, and waſhed away ous ſinnes in his owne bloud, be praiſe and glory for ever,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
